I believe in America.
我相信美國
America has made my fortune.
美國使我發了財
And I raised my daughter in the American fashion.
而我以美國方式教養我的女兒
I gave her freedom, but I taught her never to dishonor her family.
我給她自由 但也告訴她永遠不要有辱家門
She found a boyfriend, not an Italian.
她交了位男友但不是義大利人
She went to the movies with him. She stayed out late.
她跟他去看電影，深夜才回家
I didn't protest.
我並沒有責罵她
Two months ago he took her for a drive with another boyfriend.
兩個月前他與另一個男孩 帶她去兜風
They made her drink whiskey
他們強灌她喝威士忌
and then they tried to take advantage of her.
然後他們想要佔她便宜
She resisted, she kept her honor.
她抵抗，她保住了名節
So they beat her like an animal.
於是他們像對動物般的毒打她
When I went to the hospital, her nose was broken,
當我到醫院時，她的鼻樑斷了
her jaw was shattered, held together by wire.
她的下巴被打碎了 必須用鋼絲綁著才不會掉下來
She couldn't even weep because of the pain.
她痛得不能哭
But I wept. Why did I weep?
但我卻哭了，我為甚麼哭呢？
She was the light of my life.
我視她如珠如寶
Beautiful girl.
長得很美麗
Now she will never be beautiful again.
現在她再也美麗不起來
Sorry.
不好意思
I went to the police, like a good American.
我…像個守法的美國人一樣 我去報警
These two boys were brought to trial.
那兩個男孩受到了審判
The judge sentenced them to three years in prison,
法官判他們有期徒刑三年
but suspended the sentence.
但緩刑
Suspended the sentence! They went free that very day!
緩刑！他們當天就沒事了！
I stood in the courtroom like a fool.
我像個傻瓜似的站在法庭中
Those two bastards, they smiled at me.
而那兩個混蛋竟朝著我笑
Then I said to my wife, "For justice, we must go to Don Corleone."
於是我對我太太說，為求公道 我們必須去找柯里昂閣下
Why did you go to the police? Why didn't you come to me first?
你去報警前為何不先來找我？
What do you want of me? Tell me anything, but do what I beg you to do.
你要我怎麼樣？你儘管吩咐 但求你一定要幫我這個忙
What is that?
幫你甚麼忙？
That I cannot do.
那個我辦不到
I'll give you anything you ask.
你要甚麼，我都會給你
I've known you many years, but this is the first time you've asked for help.
我們相識多年 這是你第一次來找我幫忙
I can't remember the last time you invited me for a cup of coffee.
我記不起你上次是何時 請我到你家去喝咖啡了
Even though my wife is godmother to your only child.
何況我太太還是你獨生女的教母
But let's be Frank here. You never wanted my friendship.
我坦白說吧！ 你從來就不想要我的友誼
And you were afraid to be in my debt.
而且你怕欠我人情
I didn't want to get into trouble.
我不想捲入是非
I understand.
我瞭解
You found Paradise in America.
你在美國發了財
You made a good living, had police protection and there were courts of law.
生意做得很好，生活過得很好 有警察和法律保護你
You didn't need a friend like me.
你不需要我這種朋友
But now you come to me and say,
但是現在你來找我說
"Don Corleone, give me justice."
柯里昂閣下，請幫我主持公道
But you don't ask with respect.
但你對我一點尊重也沒有
You don't offer friendship. You don't even think to call me Godfather.
你並不把我當朋友 你甚至不願意喊我教父
You come on my daughter's wedding day and ask me to murder for money.
你在我女兒結婚當天來我家 用錢收買我為你殺人
I ask you for justice.
我只是要求你主持公道
That is not justice. Your daughter is alive.
那不是公道，你女兒還活著
Let them suffer, then, as she suffers.
那麼讓他們像她一樣受折磨
How much shall I pay you?
我應該付你多少錢？
Bonasera, Bonasera.
包納薩拉、包納薩拉
What have I ever done to make you treat me so disrespectfully?
到底我做了甚麼？ 讓你這麼的不尊重我？
If you'd come in friendship,
如果你以朋友身份來找我
the scum that ruined your daughter would be suffering this very day.
那麼傷害你女兒的雜碎 就會受到折磨
And if an honest man like you should make enemies, they'd be my enemies.
你這種誠實人的敵人 也就是我的敵人
And then they would fear you.
那麼，他們就會怕你
Be my friend?
當我的朋友？
Godfather?
教父
Good.
很好
Some day, and that day may never come, I'll ask a service of you.
他日我或需要你的幫忙 也可能不會有那麼一天
But until that day
但在那一天到來之前
accept this justice as a gift on my daughter's wedding day.
收下這份公道 做為小女結婚之禮
- Gràzie, Godfather. - Prego.
-謝謝，教父 -別客氣
Give this to Clemenza.
這件事交給克裏曼沙
I want people that aren't going to get carried away.
我要用可靠的人，頭腦清醒的人
We're not murderers, in spite of what this undertaker says.
我們不是謀殺犯，下手別太重
- Where's Michael? - Don't worry, he'll be here.
-麥克在哪？ -別擔心，他一會就來
We're not taking the picture without Michael.
沒有麥克我不照相
- What's the matter? - It's Michael.
-甚麼事？ -麥克的事
Don Barzini.
你好，巴西尼閣下
Hey, Paulie! Let me have some wine.
保利，讓我喝點酒
Paulie! More wine.
保利，再來點酒
- You look terrific on the floor. - Are you a dance judge or something?
-你看起來棒極了 -你是裁判還是甚麼？
Take a walk and do your job.
閃開吧，到附近晃晃 做你的工作
Sandra, watch the kids. Don't let them run wild.
僊杜拉，幫個忙 別讓孩子亂跑，好嗎？
You watch yourself, all right?
你看好你自己，好嗎？
20, 30 grand. In small bills, cash.
兩三萬元小鈔，全是現金
In that little silk purse.
全在那個小絲袋裡
If this were somebody else's wedding... Sfortunato!
如果這是我的婚禮我就發財了
Hey, Paulie!
保利，接住吧！
Stupid jerk!
你這個笨蛋！
What's the matter?
怎麼回事？
- Have to go back to work. - Tom.
-我得回去工作了 -湯姆
No Sicilian can refuse any request on his daughter's wedding day.
這是婚禮的一部分
Don Corleone, I'm honored and grateful that you have invited me.
柯里昂閣下 能受邀到貴府深感榮幸
Get out of here! It's a private party. Go on!
你們在幹甚麼？滾！ 這是私人宴會，快滾
What is it? It's my sister's wedding.
這算甚麼？是我妹妹的婚禮
Goddamn FBI don't respect nothing!
該死的聯邦密探甚麼都不尊重
Come here, come here, come here!
過來這！
But towards the end, he was paroled to help with the American war effort,
…但最後他獲假釋去為美國作戰
so for six months he's worked in my pastry shop.
過去六個月，他在我的糕餅店做事
Nazorine, what can I do for you?
納色利，我的朋友 我能為你做甚麼？
Now that the war is over,
現在戰爭結束了
this boy, Enzo, they want to repatriate him back to Italy.
這男孩，安索 他們要把他遣返義大利
Godfather, I have a daughter. You see, she and Enzo...
教父，我有個女兒，她和安索…
You want Enzo to stay in this country, and your daughter to be married.
你要安索留在這個國家 和你女兒成親
You understand everything.
你甚麼都瞭解，謝謝
Mr. Hagen. Thank you.
哈金先生，謝謝
Wait till you see the wedding cake I made for your daughter!
待會看看我為你女兒 做的結婚蛋糕
The bride, the groom and the angel...
這麼高…還有一對新人和天使
- Who should I give this job to? - Not to our paisan.
-這件事我該交給誰去辦？ -別給我們這個選區
Give it to a Jew Congressman in another district.
給別地區的猶太籍眾議員 名單上還有誰？
Hey, Michael!
你好！麥克！
He's not on the list, but Luca Brasi wants to see you.
路卡布拉西不在名單上 但他想要見你
Is this necessary?
這個…有這個必要嗎？
He didn't expect to be invited to the wedding, so he wanted to thank you.
他沒料到會受邀參加婚禮 所以要向你致謝
Don Corleone, I'm honored and grateful that you have invited me
柯里昂閣下，在令嬡婚禮這天
on the wedding day of your daughter.
能受邀到貴府深感榮幸
May their first child be a masculine child.
希望他們早生貴子
Michael...
麥克！
That man over there is talking to himself.
那邊的那個人在自言自語
See that scary guy over there?
看到那邊那個嚇人的傢伙了嗎？
- He's a very scary guy. - What's his name?
-他很叫人害怕 -他是誰？叫甚麼名字？
His name is Luca Brasi. He helps my father out sometimes.
他叫做路卡布拉西 有時候替家父辦事
Michael, he's coming over here!
麥克！等一下，他過來了
You look terrific!
你氣色好極了！
My brother Tom Hagen, Miss Kay Adams.
家兄湯姆哈金，這是凱亞當斯
Your father's been asking for you.
你父親要見你
- Very nice to meet you. - Nice to meet you.
-幸會！ -幸會
Why does your brother have a different name?
若他是你哥哥，為何不同姓？
My brother Sonny found Tom Hagen in the street.
小時候在街上
He had no home, so my father took him in.
發現湯姆無家可歸 所以家父收養了他
He's been with us ever since.
從此他就和我們住在一起了
He's a good lawyer.
他是個好律師
Not a Sicilian. I think he's going to be consigliere.
不是西西里人，但我想他會當軍師
- What's that? - That's a,
-那是甚麼？ -那是…
like a counselor, an advisor. Very important for the family.
像是個顧問 在家族中的地位非常重要
You like your lasagna?
你的扁形通心麵還好吧？
Don Corleone.
柯里昂閣下
I'm honored and grateful
在令嬡的婚禮受到邀請
that you have invited me to your daughter's wedding.
深感榮幸與感激
On the day of your daughter's wedding.
在令嬡結婚的當天
And I hope that their first child will be a masculine child.
我希望他們能早生貴子
I pledge my ever-ending loyalty.
這是我一點小小的心意
- For your daughter's bridal purse. - Thank you, Luca. Most valued friend.
-祝福他們倆白頭偕老 -謝謝你，路卡，我最珍貴的朋友
Don Corleone, I'm going to leave you now, because I know you're busy.
柯里昂閣下，我曉得你忙 我先告退了
Thank you.
謝謝
Signora Corleone!
柯里昂夫人
No!
不！…
Senator Cauley apologized for not coming, but said you'd understand.
科利參議員對不能親自來致歉 他說你會諒解的
Also some of the judges. They've all sent gifts.
還有一些法官也一樣 他們都送了禮物
What is that outside?
外面是怎麼回事？
Johnny! Johnny!
強尼！…
I love you!
我愛你！
He came all the way from California. I told you he'd come!
他大老遠由加州趕來參加婚禮 我告訴過你他會來的
- He's probably in trouble again. - He's a good godson.
-已經兩年了，他也許又有麻煩 -他是個好教子
Johnny, Johnny! Sing a song!
強尼！…唱首歌
You never said you knew Johnny Fontane!
麥克！你從未告訴我 你認得強尼方亭
- Sure. You want to meet him? - Great! Sure.
-你想見他嗎？ -當然！
- My father helped him with his career. - He did?
-家父幫他建立他的事業 -真的？
How?
怎麼做的？
- Let's listen to this song. - Michael...
-我們先聽這首唱 -不，麥克
Please, Michael. Tell me.
拜託，麥克！告訴我
When Johnny was starting out, he was signed to a personal service contract
強尼剛出道時 和一個樂隊領班簽了合約
And as his career got better and better, he wanted to get out of it.
當他走紅後，想要解除合約
Johnny is my father's godson.
強尼是家父的教子
My father went to see this bandleader.
於是家父去見樂隊負責人
He offered him $ 10,000 to let Johnny go,
而且出一萬元要他與強尼解約
but the bandleader said no.
他說不行！
So the next day my father went to see him, but this time with Luca Brasi.
第二天家父再去見他 只是這次帶著路卡布拉西
Within an hour,
一個小時之內
he signed a release for a certified check of $ 1,000.
他簽瞭解約書 只收了一千元的支票
- How did he do that? - Made him an offer he couldn't refuse.
-他是怎麼辦到的？ -家父提了個他不能拒絕的條件
- What was that? - Luca Brasi held a gun to his head,
-那是甚麼？ -路卡布拉西用槍頂著他的頭
and father said that either his brains or his signature would be on the contract.
他要是不簽字腦袋就會開花
That's a true story.
這是真實的故事
That's my family, Kay. It's not me.
凱，那是我的家庭，不是我
I'll take care of it.
我會處理的
Tom...
湯姆！
I want you to find Santino. Tell him to come to the office.
叫山提諾來我的辦公室
How are you, Fredo?
你好嗎？弗雷多
My brother Fredo, this is Kay Adams.
家兄弗雷多，這位是凱亞當斯
- Hi. - How are you doing?
-你好 -你好嗎？
- This is my brother Mike. - Are you having a good time?
-這是舍弟麥克 -玩的愉快嗎？
Yeah. This is your friend?
這是你的朋友？
I don't know what to do. My voice is weak. It's weak.
我不知道該怎麼辦 我的嗓子很虛弱，很虛弱
Anyway, if I had this part in the picture, it puts me right back on top again.
總之我若能得到那部戲的角色 我會再次走紅的
But this... man won't give it to me, the head of the studio.
但是電影公司的老闆不讓我演
- What's his name? - Woltz.
-他叫甚麼名字？ -華爾斯
He won't give it to me, and he says there's no chance.
他不肯讓我演 而且還說門都沒有
Sonny?
山尼？
- Sonny, are you in there? - What?
-山尼？你在裡面嗎？ -甚麼事？
The old man wants you.
老頭子要見你
One minute.
好，馬上去
A month ago he bought the movie rights to this book, a best-seller.
一個月以前 他買下這本暢銷書的電影版權
The main character is a guy just like me.
男主角就像是我的寫照
I wouldn't even have to act.
我根本不需要演 只要當我自己即可
Godfather, I don't know what to do.
但…教父，我不知該怎麼辦？
You can act like a man! What's the matter with you?
你要表現得像個男人！ 你是怎麼回事？
Is this how you turned out? A Hollywood finocchio that cries like a woman?
這就是你在好萊塢學到的？ 哭的像個女人？
"What can I do? What can I do?" What is that nonsense?
該怎麼辦？怎麼辦？ 算甚麼鬼話？
Ridiculous.
豈有此理！
- You spend time with your family? - Sure I do.
-你有花時間與家人共聚嗎？ -我當然有
Good.
很好
Because a man who doesn't spend time with his family can never be a real man.
因為不抽空陪家人的男人 不是真正的男人
You look terrible. I want you to eat.
你看來糟透了，我要你多吃點
Rest, and in a month this Hollywood big shot will give you what you want.
好好休息，從現在起一個月內 好萊塢大亨會讓你願望成真
It's too late, they start shooting in a week.
太遲了 他們一週內就要開拍了
I'm going to make him an offer he can't refuse.
我會給他一個 他無法拒絕的提議
Just go outside and enjoy yourself, and forget about all this nonsense.
現在你到外面去好好的玩
- I want you to leave it all to me. - All right.
-其他的交給我來辦 -好的
- What time does my daughter leave? - Soon, after they cut the cake.
-我女兒女婿何時離開？ -切完蛋糕後的幾分鐘
Do we give your son-in-law something important?
你的新女婿要給重要職務嗎？
Never. Give him a living, but never discuss the family business with him.
永遠不要！讓他們過好日子 但別讓他插手家族中的事
- What else? - Virgil Sollozzo called.
-還有甚麼事？ -威爾斯索拉索來過電話
- We'll have to see him next week. - When you come back from California.
-下週我們必須安排跟他見面 -等你從加州回來我們再討論
- When am I going to California? - Tonight.
-我何時要去加州了？ -我要你今晚去
I want you to talk to this movie big shot and settle this business for Johnny.
我要你和這個電影大亨談談 把強尼的事擺平
If there's nothing else, I'd like to go to my daughter's wedding.
若沒有其他事 我想去參加我女兒的婚禮了
Carlo, we're going to take the picture.
卡洛，我們要拍照了
Wait a minute.
等一下
No, Michael. Not me.
不，麥克，我不行
Okay, that's it. Just like that. Hold it!
好了，就是這樣，別動！
I was sent by a friend of Johnny Fontane.
我是強尼方亭的朋友派來的
This friend would give his friendship to Mr. Woltz,
他的朋友是我的委託人 若是華爾斯先生能幫他個小忙
if Mr. Woltz would grant us a favor.
他將會感激不盡
Woltz is listening.
繼續說下去
Give Johnny the part in that war film you're starting next week.
把你下週開拍的 新片男主角讓強尼擔任
And what favor would your friend grant Mr. Woltz?
他的朋友會回報我甚麼好處？
He could make your future union problems disappear.
你若有工會問題 我的委託人能擺平
And one of your stars has just moved from marijuana to heroin.
而你旗下一位抽大麻的大牌 現在吸起海洛因了
Are you trying to muscle me? Listen, you son-of-a-bitch!
-你想要威脅我嗎？ -絕對沒有，我只是…
Let me lay it on the line.
讓我對你及你的老闆說清楚 不管他是何許人
Johnny Fontane will never get that movie!
強尼方亭絕對得不到那個角色
No matter how many Dago Guinea greaseballs come out of the woodwork!
我不在乎有多少義大利的 移民來找我麻煩
- I'm German-Irish. - Listen here, my Kraut-Mick friend.
-我是德裔愛爾蘭人 -坦白告訴你，德國朋友
- I'm going to make trouble for you! - I'm a lawyer. I haven't threatened...
你大禍臨頭了 你甚至不會曉得是誰扁你
I know New York's big lawyers. Who are you?
我認識紐約的每位大律師 你是誰？
I have a special practice. I handle one client.
我的執業情況特別 只為一位委託人辦事
I'll wait for your call.
你有我的電話號碼 我等你電話
By the way, I admire your pictures very much.
告訴你，我很喜歡你的電影
Check him out.
摸清他的底細
- It's really beautiful. - Look at this.
-真是美極了 -看看這個
- It used to decorate a King's palace. - Very nice.
-原本是用來裝飾王宮的 -很漂亮
Why didn't you say you work for Corleone?
你為何不說你為柯里昂閣下做事？
I thought you were some cheap hustler Johnny was running in.
我以為你只是個市井流氓 是強尼派來勒索我的
- I only use his name when necessary. - How's your drink?
除非真的必要 否則我不想提起他的名字
You do appreciate beauty, don't you?
你的眼光應該不錯吧？
There you are. $600,000 on four hoofs.
這裡！這匹馬價值六十萬元
I bet Russian czars never paid that for a single horse.
我敢說俄國沙皇 也從未在馬身上花那麼大筆錢
Khartoum.
達通！
I'm not going to race him, though. I'm going to put him out to stud.
不過我不會用牠們來比賽 我要牠們當種馬
Thanks, Tony.
-謝謝，湯尼！ -不必客氣！
Let's get something to eat.
我們去吃點東西吧！
Corleone is Johnny's godfather.
柯里昂是強尼的教父
To the Italian people that's a very sacred, close relationship.
對義大利人而言 那是種宗教上神聖的親密關係
I respect it. Tell him to ask me anything else.
我很敬重這點 告訴他除了這件事
This favor I can't give him.
我甚麼都答應
He never asks a second favor when he's been refused the first.
他被拒絕一次後 不會再要求第二次
You don't understand. Johnny Fontane never gets that movie.
你不瞭解 強尼方亭永遠別想演那部電影
That part is perfect for him. It'll make him a big star.
他很適合那個角色 會讓他成為巨星
I'm going to run him out of the business, and let me tell you why.
但我要讓他走投無路 我告訴你為甚麼
Johnny Fontane ruined one of Woltz International's most valuable protégés.
強尼毀了一位華爾斯國際公司 最有前途的女星
We trained her for five years. Singing, acting, dancing lessons.
五年來我們不斷地訓練她 歌唱課、表演課、跳舞課
I spent hundreds of thousands of dollars on her, to make her a big star.
我在她身上投資了無數的金錢 我要讓她成為一位巨星
Let me be even more Frank.
讓我更坦白的告訴你
To show you that I'm not a hard-hearted man.
讓你知道我不是鐵石心腸 也不是勢利眼
She was beautiful. She was young and innocent!
她年輕漂亮，天真無邪
She's the greatest piece of ass I've had and I've had them all over the world.
我擁有她就等於擁有全世界
Then Johnny Fontane comes along with his olive oil voice and Guinea charm.
然後強尼方亭出現了 帶著磁性的嗓音加上義大利的魅力
And she runs off.
把她拐走了
She threw it all away just to make me look ridiculous!
她跑掉了使我非常難堪
And a man in my position can't afford to be made to look ridiculous!
而我這種地位的人無法忍受難堪
You get the hell out of here!
你馬上給我滾
If that goombah tries any rough stuff, tell him I'm no bandleader.
若是那混球想對我動粗 你告訴他我不是樂隊領班
Yeah, I heard that story.
我聽過那個故事了
Thank you for dinner and a very pleasant evening.
謝謝你的晚餐款待
Maybe your car can take me to the airport.
也許你能派車送我去機場
Mr. Corleone insists on hearing bad news immediately.
柯里昂先生堅持，壞消息要立刻回報
- You're not too tired, are you, Tom? - No, I slept on the plane.
-你不會太累吧？湯姆 -我在飛機上睡過了
I have the Sollozzo notes here.
我這裡有索拉索的資料
Sollozzo is known as The Turk.
眾人皆知，索拉索是土耳其人
He's supposed to be very good with a knife,
他應該善於用刀
but only in matters of business with reasonable complaint.
但只有發生利益衝突時 才會使用
His business is narcotics.
他是做毒品生意的
He has fields in Turkey, where they grow poppy.
他們在土耳其種罌粟
In Sicily he has plants to process them into heroin.
在西西里有工廠提鍊成海洛因
He needs cash, he needs protection from the police.
他需要現金，以及在毒品交易時 需要警方的保護
He'll give a piece of the action. I don't know how much.
我無法查出保護費價錢多少
The Tattaglia family is behind him here. They have to be in it for something.
在紐約是塔塔基利亞家族在保護他 他們一定也想分佔利益
- What about his prison record? - One term in Italy, one here.
-他的犯罪前科呢？ -一次在義大利，一次在這
He's known as a top narcotics man.
他是眾所周知的大毒梟
- Santino, what do you think? - A lot of money in that white powder.
-山提諾，你認為呢？ -白粉可以賺大錢
Yes. There's more money in narcotics than anything else.
我贊成，毒品比甚麼都好賺
If we don't get into it, somebody else will, maybe the five families.
就算我們不加入，別人也會 也許是五大家族之一，也許全部都會
With that money they can buy more police and political power.
他們會用毒品賺到的錢 買通警方和政客
Then they come after us.
到時就會趕上我們
Now we have unions and gambling, and that's great, but narcotics is the future.
現在我們掌握了工會及賭場 而他們卻掌握未來最好的東西，毒品
If we don't get a piece of that action, we risk everything in 10 years' time.
我們若不能分一杯羹
So? What's your answer going to be, Pop?
你的答案是甚麼呢？爸爸
Don Corleone.
柯里昂閣下
I need a man who has powerful friends.
我需要有勢力的友人
I need a million dollars in cash.
我需要一百萬元的現金
I need those politicians that you carry in your pocket, like nickels and dimes.
我需要你手中掌握的政客
- What is the interest for my family? - 30%.
-對我家族有甚麼利益？ -三成
In the first year your end should be three, four million dollars.
第一年你就可進帳三四百萬元
And then it would go up.
然後還會增加
And what is the interest for the Tattaglia family?
塔塔基利亞家族會得到甚麼好處？
My compliments.
我的敬意
I'll take care of them, out of my share.
我會從我那一份當中分給他們
So I receive 30% for finance,
我提供財務、政治
political influence and legal protection?
和法律的保護，可以分到三成
That's right.
沒錯
Why do you come to me? Why do I deserve this generosity?
你為何來找我？ 我為何值得你這麼慷慨？
If you consider a million dollars in cash just finance,
若你能考慮投資一百萬元現金
te salud Don Corleone.
我就會向你敬禮，柯里昂閣下
I said that I would see you, because I heard you were a serious man,
我肯見你是因為 我聽說你是個正直的人
to be treated with respect.
所以我以禮相待
But, I must say no to you.
但是我必須拒絕你
And I'll give you my reason.
我會告訴你原因
It's true, I have a lot of friends in politics.
沒錯，我是有很多政界的朋友
They wouldn't be friendly long if I was involved in drugs instead of gambling,
但若他們知道我在搞毒品生意
which they regard as a harmless vice, but drugs is a dirty business.
他們認為賭博只是些無傷大雅的事業 但毒品是敗壞德性的生意
But your business is... a little dangerous.
但你這種生意…有一點危險性
If you're worried about security, the Tattaglias will guarantee it.
若你還是擔心安全的問題 塔塔基利亞會做保證的
- The Tattaglias would guarantee our... - Wait a minute.
你是說塔塔基利亞家族 會保證我們的投資…
I have a sentimental weakness for my children, and I spoil them.
你看我把孩子都給寵壞了
They talk when they should listen. But anyway...
他們說話非常沒有分寸 但總之…
Signor Sollozzo, my no is final. I wish to congratulate you on your new business.
索拉索先生，我的決定還是不行 我要恭喜你的生意
I know you'll do well, and good luck.
我知道你會很成功，我祝你好運
Especially since your interests don't conflict with mine. Thank you.
尤其是你的生意不會與我的衝突 謝謝
Santino.
山提諾
Come here.
到這來
What's the matter with you?
你是怎麼回事？
Your brain is going soft from playing with that girl.
我看你和女孩子胡搞之後 腦子退化了
Never tell anybody outside the family what you're thinking again.
別讓外人知道你在想甚麼
Go on.
走吧
Tom, what's this nonsense?
湯姆，這是甚麼亂七八糟的？
It's from Johnny. He's starring in that new film.
那是強尼送的 他主演了那部新電影
- Take it away. - Take it over there.
-好了，把它拿走 -把它放到那去
And
還有
tell Luca Brasi to come in.
叫路卡布拉西到這來
I'm a little worried about this Sollozzo fellow.
我對這索拉索有點擔心
Find out what he's got under his fingernails.
我要你弄清楚他在耍甚麼把戲
Go to the Tattaglias.
到塔塔基利亞那邊去
Make them think that you're not too happy with our family
讓他們以為你與我們家族不融洽
and find out what you can.
儘量查
I got something for your mother and for Sonny
我買了東西給令堂
and a tie for Freddy, and Tom Hagen got the Reynolds pen.
還有給弗雷多的領帶 給湯姆的鋼筆
- What do you want for Christmas? - Just you.
-你聖誕節想要甚麼？ -我只要你
Andiamo, Fredo.
醒醒，弗雷多
- Tell Paulie to get the car. - Okay, Pop.
-叫保利備車，我們要走了 -好的，爸
I'll have to get it myself. Paulie called in sick this morning.
我來開車，保利今早生病了
Paulie's a good kid. I don't mind getting the car.
保利是個好孩子 我不介意自己開車
Buon natale, Caro. Gràzie.
謝謝
- Luca! I'm Bruno Tattaglia. - I know.
-路卡，我是布諾塔塔基利亞 -我知道
You know who I am?
你知道我是誰嗎？
I know you.
我認識你
You have been talking to the Tattaglia family... right?
你和塔塔基利亞家族談過了 對吧？
I think you and I can do business.
我認為我們可以一起做些生意
I need someone strong like you.
我需要像你這麼壯的人
I heard you are not happy...
我聽說你與柯里昂家族不和
Want to join me?
想加入我們嗎？
What's in it for me?
我能得到甚麼好處？
$50,000 to start with.
起薪五萬元
Not bad!
還不壞
Agreed?
同意了？
Tom! Tom Hagen. Merry Christmas.
湯姆哈金，聖誕快樂
- Glad to see you. I want to talk to you. - I haven't got time.
-我很高興遇見你，我想跟你聊聊 -我沒時間
Make time, Consigliere. Get in the car.
為我們撥點時間，軍師，上車
What are you worried about? If I wanted to kill you, you'd be dead already.
你擔心甚麼？ 我想殺你的話你早已死了
Get in.
上車
- Fredo, I'm going to buy some fruit. - Okay, Pop.
-稍候一下，弗雷多，我買點水果 -好的，爸
Merry Christmas. I want some fruit.
聖誕快樂，我要買些水果
Would you like me better if I were a nun? Like in the story.
麥克，我若是修女 你是否會更喜歡我
No.
不會
- What if I were Ingrid Bergman? - Now, that's a thought.
若我是英格麗褒曼 你是否會更喜歡我？
Michael.
麥克
No, I wouldn't like you better if you were Ingrid Bergman.
不，你若是英格麗褒曼 我不會更喜歡你的
They don't say if he's dead or alive.
上面沒說他是死是活
- Sonny, it's Michael. - Where have you been?
-山尼！我是麥克 -麥克，你到哪去了？
- Is he all right? - We don't know yet.
-他沒事吧？ -我們還不知道
There are all kinds of stories. He was hit bad, Mikey.
他傷的很重，麥克
- Are you there? - Yeah, I'm here.
-你還在嗎？ -是的，我在這
- Where have you been? I was worried. - Didn't Tom tell you I called?
-你到哪去了？我很擔心 -湯姆沒說我打過電話嗎？
No. Look, come home, kid. You should be with Mama, you hear?
聽我說，回家來 你應該在這陪媽媽的
Oh, my God.
我的天啊
Sonny!
山尼
- Who is it? - Open up, it's Clemenza.
-誰？ -開門！我是克裏曼沙
There's more news about your old man.
又有你老頭的消息了
Word is out that he's already dead.
街頭謠傳他已經死了
- What's the matter with you? - Take it easy!
-你是怎麼回事？ -山尼，別激動
- Where was Paulie? - Sick. He's been sick all winter.
-保利在哪？ -保利病了，他整個冬天都病了
- How often? - Only three, four times.
-他病了幾次？ -病了三四次
- Freddy didn't want a new bodyguard. - Pick him up now.
-弗雷多並不想另找保鑣 -馬上接他來
I don't care how sick he is. Bring him to my father's house right now.
我不管他病得有多重 只要他還在呼吸
- You want anyone sent over here? - No. Go ahead.
-好，你要我派人到這邊來嗎？ -不用！去吧！
I'm going to have a couple of our people come over to the house.
我會派幾個人到家裡來
- Hello? - Santino Corleone?
-你好 -山尼柯里昂嗎？
- Yeah. - We have Tom Hagen.
-我就是 -湯姆哈金在我們手上
In three hours he'll be released with our proposition.
約三小時後我們會釋放他
Listen to what he has to say before you do anything.
在你做任何事之前 先聽聽他說的話
What's done is done. Don't lose that famous temper of yours, Sonny.
木已成舟，先別發怒，好嗎？山尼
I'll wait.
不會的，我會等
Your boss is dead.
你的老闆死了
I know you're not in the muscle end of the family, so don't be scared.
我知道你在家族中是不喜歡動武 所以我不想要你感到害怕
I want you to help the Corleones and me.
我要你幫助柯里昂還有幫我
We got him outside his office about an hour after we picked you up.
接了你約一小時後 我們已在他辦公室外幹掉他了
Drink it.
喝吧
It's up to you to make peace between me and Sonny.
現在全看你的了 讓我與山尼和平解決一切
Sonny was hot for my deal, wasn't he?
山尼對我的主意很熱中，不是嗎？
And you knew it was the right thing to do.
而且你知道那麼做是對的
- Sonny will come after you. - That will be his first reaction, sure.
-山尼會不惜一切的來追殺你 -那會是他的第一個反應
So you have to talk sense into him. The Tattaglia family is behind me.
所以要你去勸勸他 塔塔基利亞家族全力支持我
The other New York families will go along with anything to prevent war.
紐約其他的家族 也會不惜一切防止全面的戰爭
Let's face it, with all due respect, the Don rest in peace was slipping.
讓我們面對現實吧！ 湯姆，我們全都尊敬他
Ten years ago, could I have gotten to him?
十年前我能對付他嗎？
Well, now he's dead, Tom, and nothing can bring him back.
但現在他已經死了，他死了，湯姆 沒甚麼能讓他復生
You've got to talk to Sonny, to the Caporegimes, Tessio, fat Clemenza.
所以你得和山尼談談
It's good business, Tom.
那是筆好生意，湯姆
I'll try. But even Sonny won't be able to call off Luca Brasi.
我試試看 但即使是山尼也阻止不了路卡
Yeah, well...
這個…
Let me worry about Luca.
路卡讓我來擔心
You just talk to Sonny.
你只管說服山尼
And the other two kids.
及他另外兩個兄弟
- I'll do my best. - Good.
-我盡力而為 -很好
Now you can go.
現在你可以走了
I don't like violence, Tom. I'm a businessman.
我不喜歡暴力，湯姆，我是個生意人
Blood is a big expense.
流血代價太高了
He's still alive.
他還活著
They hit him with five shots, and he's still alive!
他們打了他五槍，他還活著
That's bad luck for me, and bad luck for you if you don't make that deal.
那對我是件壞事
Your mother is at the hospital with your father.
令堂在醫院陪令尊 看起來他能度過難關，謝天謝地
It's a lot of bad blood. Sollozzo, Philip Tattaglia, Bruno Tattaglia, Ramon...
-全是塔塔基利亞家族策劃的 -你認為如何？
- You gonna kill all those guys? - Stay out of it.
-你要把那些人全殺掉？ -別插手這件事，麥克
If you get rid of Sollozzo, everything falls into line.
索拉索是關鍵 除掉他一切就好辦了
What about Luca? Sollozzo thinks he can control him.
路卡呢？ 索拉索認為他可以控制路卡
If Luca sold out, we're in a lot of trouble.
我不知道，如果路卡出賣我們 我們就有大麻煩了
- Has anyone been in touch with Luca? - We've been trying all night.
-有人能與路卡連絡上嗎？ -我試了一整夜但沒有人接
- Hey, do me a favor... - Luca never sleeps over with a broad.
麥克，幫我個忙，打電話給路卡
Well, Tom, you're consigliere. What do we do if the old man dies?
湯姆，你是軍師 若是老頭死了，我們該怎麼辦？
If we lose the old man, we lose the political contacts and half our strength.
我們萬一失去了老頭 我們就會失去政界的連繫
The other New York families might support Sollozzo to avoid a long war.
紐約其他的家族為了避免長期的戰爭 可能會聯合支持索拉索
This is almost 1946. Nobody wants bloodshed anymore.
現在是1946年了，沒有人想再流血了
If your father dies
若是令尊死了
you make the deal.
就由你做決定了，山尼
- Easy to say. He's not your father. - I'm as much a son as you or Mike.
-你說來容易，那不是你父親 -我與你跟麥克對他來說都是兒子
What is it?
甚麼事？
- Paulie, I told you to stay put. - The guy at the gates has a package.
-保利，我叫你在外面守著 -大門的人說收到一包東西
Tessio, go see what it is.
泰西歐，去看看是甚麼
- Shall I stay? - Yeah. Are you all right?
-你要我留在這？ -是的，留在這，你還好吧？
- I'm fine. - There's food. Are you hungry?
-是的，我很好 -有點吃的，你餓了嗎？
- No. - A drink? Brandy will sweat it out.
-不，沒關係的 -喝杯酒吧！一點白蘭地能讓你舒服點
Take care of that son-of-a-bitch. Paulie sold out the old man.
我要你立刻處置那個王八蛋 保利出賣了老頭，那個混蛋
- Make that the first thing on your list. - Understood.
這是你第一件先要解決的工作 明白嗎？
Mickey, tomorrow, get some guys and go to Luca's apartment.
麥克，明天你帶幾個人 到路卡的公寓去看看，等他出現
Maybe we shouldn't get Mike mixed up in this too directly.
也許我們不該讓麥克太直接涉入
Hanging around the house on the phone would be a big help.
聽我說…待在家裡接電話 那會有大幫助的
Try Luca again.
再試著打給路卡
- What's this? - A Sicilian message.
-這是甚麼？ -那是西西里人的口信
It means Luca Brasi sleeps with the fishes.
那表示路卡布拉西與魚同眠了
- I'm going. - When will you be home?
-我現在要走了 -你今晚幾點會回家？
Probably late.
我不知道，也許會很晚
- Don't forget the cannoli! - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
-別忘了油餅 -知道了
Rocco, sit on the other side. You block the rear-view mirror.
羅可，坐到另一邊去 你擋住後照鏡了
Sonny's running wild. He wants to go to mattresses already.
開始大發雷霆了 他想要跟對手開戰了
We have to find a spot on the West Side. Try 309 West 43rd Street.
我們得在西區找個地方藏匿 你試試西43街309號
- Know a good spot on the West Side? - I'll think about it.
-你知道西區有何好地方嗎？ -我想想看
Think while you're driving. I want to hit New York this month.
你開車的時候想想好嗎？ 我這個月要找一天到紐約去
Watch the kids.
倒車出去時留意小孩子
Paulie, go down 39th Street, pick up 18 mattresses and bring me the bill.
保利，我要你到39街去 去買18個墊子然後把帳單拿給我
Make sure they're clean, because the guys will be there a long time.
確定要乾淨的 因為我們要在那待段長時間
- They're clean and exterminated. - That's a bad word to use.
-它們是乾淨的，他們說消毒過 -消毒，用那個字很不好
Exterminate! Watch out, so we don't exterminate you!
消毒，聽聽這個傢伙 小心點，我們才不會為你消毒
Pull over. I've got to take a leak.
停到路旁去好嗎？我要小便
Leave the gun. Take the cannoli.
把槍留下，把油餅給我
Hey, Mike! Hey, Mikey!
麥克…
- Who is it? - Some girl.
-是誰？ -女孩子
- Hello. Kay? - How's your father?
-你好，凱 -令尊還好嗎？
He's going to make it.
他很好，他能活過來
I love you.
我愛你
- Michael? - Yeah, I know.
-麥克 -是，我知道
- Tell me you love me. - I can't talk.
-告訴我你愛我 -我不能說
Can't you say it?
你不能說嗎？
I'll see you tonight.
我們今晚見
Why don't you tell that nice girl you love her?
麥克，你為何不說你愛她
I love you with all my heart. If I don't see you again soon, I'm going to die!
我全心全意的愛你 我若不快點見到你，我會死的
Come and learn something. You might have to cook for 20 guys some day.
到這來，孩子，學點東西 有一天你也許得為20個男人煮飯
You start with a little oil, then fry some garlic.
一開始先倒點油，炸大蒜
Throw in some tomatoes, tomato paste, fry it and make sure it doesn't stick.
然後放番茄，炒一下 別讓它黏鍋底
You get it to a boil, you shove in all your sausage and meatballs.
煮開了之後，加入香腸及肉丸
Add a little bit of wine.
再加一點點酒
And a little bit of sugar. That's my trick.
以及一點點糖，那是我的秘方
Cut the crap. I have more important things for you. How's Paulie?
你別說廢話了，我有更重要的事 要讓你去做，保利呢？
You won't see him no more.
保利，你再也見不到他了
- Where are you going? - To the city.
-你要去哪？ -到城裡去
- Send bodyguards with him. - I'm going to the hospital...
-派保鑣跟他一起去 -我只是去醫院看爸爸
He'll be all right. Sollozzo knows he's a civilian.
他不會有事的 索拉索知道他是「平民」
- Be careful. - Yes, sir.
-小心點 -是的
Send somebody with him anyway.
還是派人跟他一起去
- I have to go. - Can I go with you?
-我得走了 -我能與你一起去嗎？
No, Kay. There will be detectives there, people from the press.
不，凱，那裡有刑警還有記者
I'll wait in the cab.
我在車上等你
I don't want you to get involved.
我不要你捲入這件事
When will I see you again?
我何時能再見到你？
Go back to New Hampshire, and I'll call you at your parents' house.
回新罕布夏去 我打電話去你父母家找你
- When will I see you again, Michael? - I don't know.
-我何時才能再見到你？麥克 -我不知道
What are you doing here? You're not supposed to be here.
你在這裡幹甚麼？現在不是探病時間
I'm Michael Corleone. This is my father.
我是麥克柯里昂，這是家父
What happened to the guards?
這裡沒人，守衛到哪去了？
Your father had too many visitors. They interfered with hospital service.
令尊訪客太多 妨礙了醫院的作業
The police made them leave about 10 minutes ago.
警察在十分鐘前要他們離去了
Get me Long Beach 45620, please.
請幫我接長灘45620
Nurse. Wait a minute. Stay here.
護士，等一下，先別走
Sonny, I'm at the hospital. I got here late, there's nobody here.
山尼，我是麥克，我在醫院 聽著，我很晚才到這兒，這沒有人
No Tessio's men, no detectives, nobody. Papa's all alone.
泰西歐的人不在，也沒有刑警 沒有人，爸爸單獨一個人在這
- Don't panic. - I won't panic.
-別驚慌 -我不會驚慌
I'm sorry, but you will have to leave.
我很抱歉，但你必須離去
We're going to move him to another room.
你幫我把家父移去另一間房
Can you disconnect the tubes?
現在你是否能把這個拆開
- That's out of the question! - Do you know my father?
-那是不可能的 -你認識家父嗎？
Men are coming here to kill him. Do you understand?
他們會來殺了他，懂嗎？
Help me, please.
現在請你幫我忙
- Who are you? - I am Enzo, the Baker.
-你是誰？ -我是安索，那個糕餅師
- Remember me? - Enzo.
-你還記得我吧？ -安索
You'd better go, there's going to be trouble.
是的，我是安索，你最好離開這 安索，這裡會有麻煩
If there is trouble, I'll stay here to help you. For your father.
若是有麻煩，我留在這幫你 為了令尊！
Listen. Wait for me outside, in front of the hospital, all right?
好吧！聽我說 在醫院大門外面等我，好嗎？
I'll be out in a minute.
我馬上出來
Just lie here, Pop. I'll take care of you now.
好好休息吧！爸！我會照料你的
I'm with you now.
我和你在一起
Get rid of these. Come here.
把這個丟掉，到這來
Put your hand in your pocket, like you have a gun.
把手放在口袋裡，就像你有把槍 你不會有事的
You did good.
你做得很好
I thought all you Guinea hoods were locked up!
我以為把你們這些混混全關住了
- Why isn't anyone guarding my father? - You little punk!
你在這裡幹甚麼？ 守家父的人是怎麼回事？
Don't you tell me my business! I pulled them off.
竟敢管我的事 是我把那些人全趕走的
- Stay away from this hospital! - Not until my father's room is guarded.
-你馬上離開這醫院 -除非你派人守護家父，否則我不會走
- Phil, take him in! - The kid's clean, Captain.
-菲爾，把他帶回去 -那孩子是清白的，隊長
- He's a war hero. He's never been... - I said take him in!
他是個服役榮歸的英雄 從未和黑手黨混在一起
- What's The Turk paying you? - Take a hold of him. Stand him up.
-索拉索付你多少錢來陷害家父？ -把他抓牢
Stand him up straight.
讓他站穩
I'm the Corleones' attorney. These men are hired to protect Vito Corleone.
我是柯里昂家的律師，這些人是 私家偵探，僱來保護維多柯里昂的
They're licensed to carry firearms.
他們有攜帶武器的執照
If you interfere, you'll have to appear before the judge and show 'cause.
若是你干預，我們明早法庭見
Let him go.
好了，讓他走
- What's with all the new faces? - We'll need them now.
-這些新面孔是怎麼回事？ -我們現在需要他們
After the hospital thing, Sonny got mad.
經過醫院的事之後，山尼氣瘋了
We hit Bruno Tattaglia this morning.
我們今晨四點 幹掉了布諾塔塔基利亞
Jesus Christ.
老天爺
Looks like a fortress around here.
這裡看起來像是座城堡
Tamaduch! Hey... 100 buttonmen on the street 24 hours a day.
街上一天24小時 都有一百個槍手在巡邏
That Turk shows one hair on his ass, he's dead.
那土耳其人敢露出一根汗毛 就掛了
Mike, let me look at you.
麥克，到這裡來，讓我看看你
You're beautiful, beautiful. You're gorgeous.
你漂亮極了，漂亮極了
The Turk wants to talk! Imagine the nerve of the son-of-a-bitch.
你們聽我說
- He wants a meeting today. - What did he say?
-昨晚整我們，今天想和談 -他怎麼說？
What did he say... He wants us to send Michael to hear the proposition.
他怎麼說？他要我們派麥克去
He promises that the deal is too good to refuse.
並保證那條件好到我們不會拒絕
- And Bruno Tattaglia? - That's part of the deal.
-那布諾塔塔基利亞呢？ -那是條件的一部分
- He cancels out what they did to Father. - We should listen to them.
-他作為對家父挨槍的補償 -山尼，我們該聽聽他們怎麼說
No more! Not this time, Consigliere.
不！不再聽了，軍師
No more meetings, discussions, or Sollozzo tricks.
不再和談、不再討論 不再上索拉索的當
I want Sollozzo, or we go to war...
你去跟他們說，我要索拉索 否則我們就開戰！
- The other families... - They hand me Sollozzo!
-山尼，其他家族不會支持的 -叫他們把索拉索交給我
This is business, not personal!
山尼，令尊不會喜歡的 這是生意，不能感情用事
- They shot my father... - Even that was business, not personal.
那我父親就該挨槍了？
Then business will have to suffer. Do me a favor.
那生意必須要停，行嗎？ 聽著，幫我個忙，湯姆
No more advice on how to patch things up. Just help me win.
別再建議我如何讓事情過去 只要幫我贏，好嗎？
I found out about Captain McCluskey, who broke Mike's jaw.
我查出了打斷麥克下巴 那麥克勞斯基隊長的事
He's definitely on Sollozzo's payroll, and for big money.
他肯定在索拉索的規費名單中 而且是很大一筆錢
McCluskey has agreed to be The Turk's bodyguard.
麥克勞斯基是索拉索的保鑣 你必須要瞭解，山尼
So when Sollozzo is being guarded, he's invulnerable.
當索拉索跟警察隊長勾搭上時 沒人可以碰他了
Nobody has ever gunned down a New York police captain.
過去從沒人膽敢幹掉紐約警官 那會是個大災難
All the families would come after you. The Corleone family would be outcasts!
所有五大家族都會追殺你 山尼，柯里昂家族會被孤立！
Even the old man's political protection would run for cover.
即使是老頭的政治保護都會消失
Do me a favor. Take this into consideration.
拜託你，別輕舉妄動
All right, we'll wait.
好吧！我們等
We can't wait. We can't wait.
我們不能等，我們不能等
No matter what Sollozzo says, he's going to kill Pop.
不管索拉索答應甚麼 他會殺了爸爸的
That's the key for him. We've got to get Sollozzo.
那是他的關鍵，必須幹掉索拉索
- Mike is right. - Let me ask you something.
-麥克說得對 -那個談判就沒有必要了
What about this McCluskey? What do we do with this cop?
這個麥克勞斯基呢？ 我們要拿這個條子怎麼辦？
They want to have a meeting with me, right?
他們想與我開會，對吧？
It will be me, McCluskey and Sollozzo.
那會是我、麥克勞斯基及索拉索
Let's set the meeting.
我們來安排會議
Get our informers to find out where it's going to be held.
我們查清楚會議地點在哪裡
We insist it's a public place. A bar, a restaurant.
必須是公開場所，酒吧或餐廳
Some place where there are people, so I feel safe.
人多的地方對我比較安全
They'll search me when I meet them, right?
我與他們一見面 他們會搜身，對吧
So I can't have a weapon on me.
那麼我身上不能有武器
But if Clemenza can figure out a way to have a weapon planted there for me
若克裏曼沙能想出一個辦法 能預先把武器放在那
then I'll kill them both.
那我就能殺了他們兩個
Nice college boy. Didn't want to get mixed up in the family business.
你要怎麼做？乖乖的大學生
Now you want to shoot a police captain because he slapped you?
現在因為他打了你 你就想幹掉他？
This isn't like the army! You have to get close and get their brains on your suit.
你以為這裡是甚麼？軍隊嗎？ 在一哩以外開槍打他們？
You're taking this very personal.
-山尼… -你太感情用事了
Tom, this is business and he's taking it personal.
湯姆，這是公事，而他卻感情用事
- Where does it say you can't kill a cop? - Mikey...
誰說不能殺條子的？
A cop who got mixed up in the rackets and got what was coming.
和毒販混在一起，終於得到報應
That's a terrific story. We have newspaper people on the payroll, right?
那是個好極了的故事 報社不是有我們的人嗎？
- They might like a story like that. - They might.
-他們也許對那故事有興趣 -他們也許，只是也許
It's not personal, Sonny. It's strictly business.
不是感情用事，山尼 純粹是公事
It's as cold as they come.
做過表面處理了，追蹤不到的 不用擔心指紋
I put a special tape on the trigger and the butt. Try it.
我在扳機和手把上貼了特殊膠布 來，試試看
Is the trigger too tight?
怎麼了？扳機太緊了？
My ears!
我的耳朵好辛苦
I left it noisy, so it scares away any pain-in-the-ass innocent bystanders.
我沒安裝消聲器 那樣才能嚇走旁觀的人
You've shot them both. Now what do you do?
好了，你殺了他們兩個 接下來你怎麼辦？
- Sit down, finish my dinner. - Don't fool around.
-坐下吃完我的晚餐 -別開玩笑
Let your hand drop to your side and let the gun slip out.
就讓你的手垂下，讓槍滑掉
Everybody will still think you've got it. They'll stare at your face,
每個人都認為你還拿著槍 他們會瞪著你的臉，麥克
so walk out fast, but don't run.
所以快步離開那地方但不要跑
Don't look anybody in the eye, but don't look away either.
別直視任何人，但也不要看其他地方
They'll be scared stiff, so don't worry about nothing.
他們會怕得不敢瞪你 相信我，不必擔心
You'll be all right. You'll take a vacation, nobody knows where,
你若可以全身而退 可以休個長假到哪裡都可以
and we'll catch the hell.
而我們會處理善後
- How bad do you think it will be? - Pretty goddamn bad.
-你認為後果會有多糟？ -他媽的蠻糟的
All the other families will probably line up against us.
可能所有的家族會聯合對付我們 那沒關係的
Been 10 years since the last one. You have to stop them at the beginning.
上一次到現在已有十年了 要先發制人
Like they should have stopped Hitler in Munich, not letting him get away with it.
就像要在慕尼黑制止希特勒一樣 他們容忍了希特勒，麻煩就大了
You know, Mike, we were all proud of you. Being a hero and all.
知道嗎？麥克，我們都以你為榮 你是個英雄
Your father too.
你父親也是
Nothing. Not a hint. Absolutely nothing.
沒有任何線索，甚麼都沒有
Even Sollozzo's people don't know where the meeting will be held.
索拉索的人也不知在哪裡開會
How much time do we have?
我有多少時間？
They're going to pick you up outside Jack Dempsey's in an hour and a half.
一小時半以後 他們在達西路口接你上車
- We could put a tail on them. - Sollozzo would lose our ass.
-我們派個人追蹤他們 -索拉索會在街上亂轉甩掉我們的人
- What about the negotiator? - He's playing pinochle with my men.
-來找我們談判的人呢？ -他在那邊和我的手下玩紙牌
- He's happy. They're letting him win. - Too risky. Maybe we should call it off.
他很高興，我們在讓他贏
The negotiator plays cards until Mike is back safe.
要麥克平安回來 我們才會讓那個人走的
- He could blast whoever is in the car. - They'll expect that.
-何不乾脆幹掉車上的人呢？ -太危險了，他們會注意的
Sollozzo might not even be in the car, Sonny!
索拉索也許根本就不在車上
I'll get it.
我來接
Louis' restaurant in the Bronx.
布朗區的路易士餐廳
- Is it reliable? - My man in McCluskey's precinct.
-可靠嗎？ -麥克勞斯基的分局裡有我的人
A police captain is on call 24 hours a day. He'll be there between 8 and 10.
隊長必須24小時待命 他八點到十點會去那裡
- Anybody know this joint? - Sure, I do. It's perfect for us.
-有誰知道那個地方？ -我知道，對我們太理想了
A small family place, good food. Everyone minds his business. Perfect.
家庭餐廳，食物精美 各吃各的，太理想了
They've got an old-fashioned toilet. You know, the box and the chain thing.
彼得，那兒有個舊式馬桶 你知道就是水箱有吊鏈的那種
We might be able to tape the gun behind it.
我們或許可把槍用膠帶綁在那
All right. Mike, you go to the restaurant,
好的，麥克，你去餐廳
you eat, talk for a while, you relax. Make them relax.
你一面吃一面聊，別緊張 也可以使對方輕鬆下來
Then you go to take a leak. No, better still, you ask permission to go.
然後你站起來去上廁所 你得先徵求對方同意再去
Then you come back blasting. Two shots in the head apiece.
回來時就開槍 別失誤，對準頭顱各開兩槍
I want somebody very good to plant that gun.
聽著，我要一個好手去藏槍
I don't want him coming out with just his dick.
我不希望我弟弟出來時 手無寸鐵
- The gun will be there. - You drive him and pick him up.
-槍會在那的 -你開車送他，事後再接他回來
Let's move.
來吧！我們動身了
Did he tell you to drop the gun right away?
他告訴過你事成之後立刻丟槍嗎？
Yeah, a million times.
幾百萬次了
Don't forget. Two shots apiece in the head as soon as you come out.
切記！朝每人頭部開兩槍 一出廁所後就打
How long do you think it will be before I can come back?
你們認為要多久我才能回家？
At least a year.
至少得一年，麥克
I'll square it with Mom, that you're not seeing her before you leave and...
我會轉告媽 你臨走前不能去看她
I'll get a message to that girlfriend when the time is right.
我會告訴你女朋友的
Take care.
保重！
Take care, Mike.
保重！麥克
I'm glad you came. I hope we can straighten everything out.
我很高興你來了，麥克 希望我們能把事情談妥
It's not the way I wanted things to go. It should never have happened.
這種事太可怕了 我並不希望發生這種事
I want to straighten everything out. I don't want my father bothered again.
我會在今晚解決一切 我不希望我爸煩心
I swear on my children that he won't be, Mike.
-會解決的，麥克 -我以我孩子之名發誓
But you have to keep an open mind when we talk.
不過談的時候，你得坦誠才行
I hope you're not a hothead like Sonny. You can't talk business with him.
希望你不像令兄的壞脾氣 簡直沒辦法和他談正事
He's a good kid.
他是個好孩子
I'm sorry about the other night, Mike.
那晚的事我很抱歉，麥克
I've got to frisk you, so turn around. On your knees, facing me.
我得搜你的身，轉過來 跪在椅子上，臉向我
I guess I'm getting too old for my job. Too grouchy.
我想我幹這行已經嫌老了 太多話了
Can't stand the aggravation. You know how it is.
受不了別人的激怒 你該明白吧
He's clean.
他沒帶傢伙
Going to Jersey?
到新澤西去？
Maybe.
也許
Nice work, Lou.
漂亮極了，路
- How's the food in this restaurant? - Try the veal. It's the best in the city.
這裡的義大利菜味道還可以吧？
I'll have it.
給我來一份
- I'm going to speak Italian to Mikey. - Go ahead. 696.1
-好了，我要和麥克用義大利文交談 -請便
- I'm sorry. - Forget about it. 696.2
（義大利文）
What's most important to me
對我而言最重要的是
is that I have a guarantee. No more attempts on my father's life.
保證家父的性命安全
What guarantees can I give you? I'm the hunted one!
你要我怎麼保證？麥克 我也是驚弓之鳥
I missed my chance. You think too much of me, kid.
我也失手 你太看重我了，孩子
I'm not that clever.
我沒有那麼精明
All I want is a truce.
我想要的只是息戰而已
I have to go to the bathroom. Is it all right?
我必須要上廁所，可以嗎？
When you got to go, you got to go.
想去就去吧
I frisked him. He's clean.
我搜過了，他沒帶傢伙
Don't take too long.
別去太久
I've frisked a thousand punks. 708.1
我搜過好幾千人了
Everything all right? 708.2
（義大利文）
Hey, come on. 708.9
好了，轉進來
Joe, you take over.
好了，你接手
I love you, Grandpa. 710.1
我愛你，爺爺
I'm sorry, Pa. He doesn't know you yet.
對不起，爸，他還不認識你
- Hey, big guy. Give it to Grandpa. - Okay.
-小傢伙，唸給爺爺聽！ -好
" I hope you get well, Grandpa, and wish I see you soon. Your grandson Frank."
我祝你早日康復，爺爺，我希望能 快點見到你，愛你的孫子，法蘭克
Go with your mother.
走吧！到外面去
Take them downstairs.
把他們帶到樓下去吧！
Go on, Carlo, you too.
走吧！卡洛，你也是
Go on.
走吧
- What's the matter with you, Carlo? - Shut up and set the table.
-你怎麼了？卡洛 -閉嘴，去擺桌子吧！
Since McCluskey's killing, the police have cracked down on our operations.
自從麥克勞斯基被殺後 警方瓦解了我們多數業務
And also the other families. There's been a lot of bad blood.
其他的家族也是一樣，犧牲很多
They hit us, so we hit them back.
他們攻擊我們，我們反擊
Through our newspaper contacts we've been able to put out material
透過我們報社中的連繫 我們提供了不少內幕
about McCluskey's link with Sollozzo in the drug rackets.
很多麥克勞斯基 跟毒販索拉索勾結的事
So things are loosening up.
所以風聲已經沒有那麼緊了
And I'm sending Fredo to Las Vegas,
還有我派弗雷多去拉斯維加斯
under the protection of Don Francesco of L.A.
在洛杉磯的法蘭西斯科閣下 會給予他保護
- I want him to rest. - I'm going to learn the casino business.
-我要他休息一會兒 -我要去學賭場的事
Where's Michael?
麥克在哪？
It was Michael who killed Sollozzo.
殺索拉索的是麥克
But he's safe. We're starting to work to bring him back.
不過他很安全，別擔心 我們會把他弄回來的
I want you to find out where that old pimp Tattaglia is hiding.
你查出塔塔基利亞躲在哪兒沒？
I want him now.
我要他的命！現在！
Sonny, things are starting to loosen up.
-聽我說，山尼 -甚麼事？
If you go after Tattaglia, all hell will break loose. Pop can negotiate.
你若去追塔塔基利亞 又會引起一場大戰的
- He must get better first. I'll decide... - War is costly. We can't do business.
不，爸爸在身體好轉之前 甚麼都不能做
- Neither can they. Don't worry about it! - We can't afford a stalemate.
-他們也不行，別擔心 -他們沒有我們損失那麼大
- No more stalemate. I'll kill the bastard! - You're getting a great reputation!
我會以宰了那老混蛋來做結束
Do as I say! If I had a Sicilian wartime consigliere, I wouldn't be in this shape!
依照我叫你做的去做
Pop had Genco. Look what I got.
爸爸有傑安可，看看我有甚麼？
I'm sorry. I didn't mean that.
對不起，我不是有意的
Ma made a little dinner. It's Sunday.
媽媽煮了晚餐，今天是星期天
Niggers are having a good time with our policy banks in Harlem.
黑人對我們哈林區的 銀行新政策非常滿意
Driving new Cadillacs, paying 50% on a bet.
開著新凱迪拉克 我先幫他們付一半的錢
That's because they've started making big money.
從他們開始賺錢時 我就知道這會發生
Papa never talked business at the table.
爸爸從來不在餐桌上 當著孩子們談他的公事
- Shut up, Connie... - Don't you ever tell her to shut up.
-閉嘴，康妮… -不准你叫她閉嘴，知道嗎？
Don't interfere.
別干預
I'd like to talk to you after dinner. I could do more for the family...
山尼、湯姆 吃過飯後，我想與你們談談
I kiss your hand, Don Tommasino.
我向你致敬，湯馬西諾閣下
Why are you so far from the house?
你為何離房子那麼遠？
You know I'm responsible to your father for your life.
你可知萬一你出了事 我要向令尊負責的
The bodyguards are here.
保鑣們都在這
It's still dangerous...
還是十分危險
We've heard from Santino in New York...
我聽紐約的山提諾說的
Your enemies know you're here.
你的敵人知道你在這了
Did Santino say when I can go back?
山提諾有沒有說，我何時能回去？
Not yet.
還不行
It's out of the question.
目前是不可能的
Where are you going now?
你現在要去哪裡？
To Corleone.
柯里昂村
Take my car.
坐我的車去
I want to walk.
我想走路
Be careful.
小心點
Where have all the men gone?
所有的男人都到哪去了？
They're all dead from vendettas.
他們全都在戰爭中死了
There are the names of the dead.
這裡是死者的姓名
Mamma Mia what a beauty.
我的老天！好一個美女
I think you got hit by the thunderbolt.
你好像中邪了一樣
In Sicily women are more dangerous than shotguns.
在西西里，女人比獵槍還危險
Did you have a good hunt?
打獵有收穫嗎？
You know all the girls around here?
你認識這一帶所有的女孩嗎？
We saw some real beauties.
我們看到幾位真正的美人
One of them struck our friend like a thunderbolt.
其中一位讓我們的朋友觸電了
She would tempt the devil himself.
她可真夠騷了
Really put together.
她全身上下都很美
Such hair, such mouth!
那麼漂亮的頭髮、嘴
The girls around here are beautiful... but virtuous.
這一帶的女孩都很美 而且很貞潔
This one had a purple dress...
這個穿著紫色衣服
And a purple ribbon in her hair.
頭髮上綁著紫色的緞帶
A type more Greek than Italian.
看起來像希臘人而非義大利人
Do you know her?
你認識她嗎？
There's no girl like that in this town.
在本鎮沒有那樣子的女孩
My God, I understand!
我的天！我明白了
What's wrong?
有甚麼不對了？
Let's go.
我們走
It's his daughter.
是他女兒
Tell him to come here.
叫他出來
Call him.
去叫他
Fabrizio, you translate.
法布利奇歐，你翻譯
I apologize if I offended you.
我若冒犯了你，我道歉
I'm a stranger in this country.
我初到貴地
I meant no disrespect to you or your daughter.
我無意冒犯你和令嬡
I'm an American, hiding in Sicily.
我是個美國人 到西西里來避風頭
My name is Michael Corleone.
我的名字是麥克柯里昂
There are people who'd pay a lot of money for that information.
有人會為了錢 而出賣我在此的消息
But then your daughter would lose a father
但那樣令嬡會失去父親
instead of gaining a husband.
而不是得到一位丈夫
I want to meet your daughter.
我想認識你女兒
With your permission, and under the supervision of your family.
但要在你的同意下 及在你的家人的監督之下
With all respect.
我絕對是誠心誠意
Come to my house Sunday morning. My name is Vitelli.
星期天早上到我家來 我叫維提
Apollonia. 807.2
艾波洛妮亞
Thank you. 807.5
謝謝
I'll knock you dizzy.
等我回來幹你
Save it for the library.
廢話少說
We've got to pick up my sister.
來吧！我們得去接我妹妹
What's the matter?
怎麼了？
- It was my fault! - Where is he?
-是我的錯 -他在哪？
It was my fault. I hit him.
山尼，拜託，是我的錯 山尼，是我的錯
I started a fight with him. I hit him, so he hit me...
是我先開始打他的！ 求你，山尼，我先打他的
I'm just going to get a doctor to take a look at you.
我只是叫醫生來看你，好嗎？
Sonny, please don't do anything.
山尼，求你別動手
What's the matter with you? What am I going to do?
好，你是怎麼了？我會怎麼做？
Make that baby an orphan before he's born?
我會讓你肚裡的孩子做遺腹子嗎？
You spic slobs still betting Yankees?
這些傢伙把洋基隊打得慘兮兮
Tell them to stop taking in action.
叫他們不要再接受投注了
We lost enough money last week.
我們上週末輸的錢夠多了
Come here, come here!
卡洛，到這來…
If you touch my sister again, I'll kill you.
你再碰我妹妹一下，我會殺了你
Hey! We weren't expecting you, Kay. You should call.
沒想到你會來，凱 怎麼不先打個電話來
Yes, I have. I've tried writing and calling.
我有打，我寫過信也打過電話
- I want to reach Michael. - Nobody knows where he is.
-我要和麥克連絡 -沒有人知道他在哪
All we know is that he's all right.
我們知道他沒事但如此而已
- What was that? - An accident, but nobody was hurt.
-怎麼了？ -那是件車禍但沒有人受傷
Tom, will you give this letter to Michael. Please?
湯姆，請你把這封信交給麥克 好嗎？
If I accepted that, a court could prove I have knowledge of his whereabouts.
我若接受了 法院可以證實我曉得他在哪裡
He'll get in touch with you.
你有耐心點，凱 他會與你連絡的，好嗎？
I let my cab go, so can I call another one, please?
我讓我的計程車走了 我是否能進去打電話叫一輛？
Come on. Sorry.
來吧！對不起，來吧！
- Who is this? - A friend of Carlo.
-你是哪位？ -我是卡洛的朋友
Tell him that I can't make it tonight until later.
你告訴他我今晚沒空
Bitch!
賤人
- Dinner's on the table. - I'm not hungry.
-晚餐在桌上了 -我還不餓
- The food is getting cold. - I'll eat out later.
-晚餐在桌上快涼了 -我有約了
- You just told me to make you dinner! - Vafangool!
-你剛叫我給你做晚餐的 -滾開好嗎？
I'll vafangool you!
你才滾開
She has a filthy mouth, this Guinea brat.
你這個義大利婊子
That's it, break it all, you spoiled Guinea brat. Break it all!
好，全都打破了！ 你這被寵壞的女娃！全打破了！
Why don't you bring your whore home for dinner?
你為何不把那個妓女 帶回家吃晚飯？
Maybe I will.
也許我會，有何不可？
- Clean it up! - Like hell I will!
-現在把它清乾淨！ -我不要！我才不要！
You skinny, spoiled brat. Clean it up! Clean it up!
清乾淨！賤人
Clean it up. Clean that up, you...
清乾淨！
Clean it!
清乾淨！
Clean it up! Yeah, kill me. Be a murderer, like your father!
來！殺我！ 像你爸一樣當兇手！
- All you Corleones are murderers! - I hate you!
來吧！你們姓柯里昂的全是兇手
Come on, kill me!
來吧！賤人，來吧！殺我！
Get out of here!
滾！
- I hate you! - Now I'll kill you.
-我恨你！ -快點！否則我要殺你了
You Guinea brat. Get out of here!
你這義大利賤貨，滾出來
Connie, what's the matter? I can't hear you.
康妮，怎麼回事？ 我聽不見你說的，甚麼事？
Connie, talk louder. The baby's crying.
康妮，說大聲點，孩子在哭
Santino, I can't understand. I don't know.
山提諾，我聽不懂，我不明白
Yeah, Connie.
甚麼事？康妮？
You wait there.
聽我說，你在那等著
No, you just wait there.
不，你在那等著就對了
Son-of-a-bitch.
王八蛋！
- Son-of-a-bitch! - What's the matter?
-怎麼回事？ -王八蛋！
Open the goddamn gate! Get off your ass.
快開門，站起來
Sonny!
山尼
- Sonny. - Get out of here!
-山尼 -滾開
Go after him, go on!
跟他一起去，快點
Son-of-a-bitch. Come on!
王八蛋，快點…
Give me a drop.
把那個給我
My wife is crying upstairs.
我太太在樓上哭
I hear cars coming to the house.
我聽見車子到家裡來
Consigliere of mine,
我的好軍師
tell your Don what everyone seems to know.
所有人都知道 只有我毫不知情
I didn't tell Mama anything.
我沒告訴媽任何事
I was about to come up and wake you and tell you.
我正預備去叫醒你，並告訴你
But you needed a drink first.
但你需要先喝杯酒
Well, now you've had your drink.
現在你喝過酒了
They shot Sonny on the causeway. He's dead.
他們在收費站殺了山尼 他死了
I want no inquiries made.
我不要追查此事
I want no acts of vengeance.
我不要復仇
I want you to arrange a meeting
我要你安排一次會議
with the heads of the five families.
與五大家族的族長
This war stops now.
這場火拚該終止了
Call Bonasera.
打電話給包納薩拉
I need him now.
我現在需要他了
This is Tom Hagen. I'm calling for Vito Corleone, at his request.
我是湯姆哈金 維多柯里昂要我打這個電話
You owe your Don a service.
你欠教父一次人情
He has no doubt that you will repay it.
他相信你會回報他的
He will be at your funeral parlor in one hour.
他在一小時後會到你的殯儀館去 請在那等待
Well, my friend, are you ready to do me this service?
我的朋友 你預備為我服務了嗎？
Yes. What do you want me to do?
是的，但你要我怎麼做？
I want you to use all your powers and all your skills.
我要你盡你一切的力量和技巧 好好為他化妝
I don't want his mother to see him this way.
我不要他母親看到他這個樣子
Look how they massacred my boy.
看看他們是怎麼對我的孩子？
It's safer to teach you English!
教你英文會安全一點
I know English...
我會英文
Monday, Tuesday, Thursday, Wednesday, Friday, Sunday, Saturday.
星期一、星期二、星期四、星期三 星期五、星期日、星期六
Greetings, Don Tommasino.
你好，湯馬西諾閣下
How are things in Palermo?
家裡的一切都還好吧？
Michael is teaching me to drive... watch, I'll show you.
麥克在教我開車 我開給你看
How are things in Palermo?
家裡的一切都還好吧？
Young people don't respect anything anymore...
年輕人不再尊重任何事了
times are changing for the worse.
時代越變越糟
This place has become too dangerous for you.
這地方對你已變得太危險了
I want you to move to a villa near Siracusa... right now.
我要你搬到西拉古莎附近的別墅
What's wrong?
有甚麼不對了？
Bad news from America.
由美國傳來的壞消息
Your brother, Santino, they killed him.
你哥哥山尼，他們殺了他！
Let's go... you promised.
我們走了！你答應的
Fabrizio!
-法布利奇歐！ -甚麼事？
Are you driving yourself, Boss? Is your wife coming with you?
你要自己開嗎？老闆
No, take her to her father's house until things are safe.
不，我要你送她回娘家 等一切安全點再說
Okay, anything you say.
好的，隨你吩咐，老闆
Calo, where is Apollonia?
卡羅，艾波洛妮亞呢？
She's going to surprise you. She wants to drive.
她想給你個驚喜，她要開車
She'll make a good American wife.
她會當個好的美國太太
Wait, I'll get the baggage.
等一下，我去拿行李
Fabrizio!
法布利奇歐
Where are you going?
你要去哪？
Wait there! I'll drive to you.
麥克，在那等，我開過去
No, Apollonia!
不！艾波洛妮亞…
Don Barzini, I want to thank you for helping me organize this meeting,
巴西尼閣下 謝謝你幫我安排這次會議
and the other heads of the five families from New York and New Jersey.
還有紐約和新澤西 其他五大家族的族長
Carmine Cuneo from the Bronx,
布朗區的卡麥克裏安諾
and from Brooklyn
以及…布魯克林的
Philip Tattaglia.
菲立浦塔塔基利亞
And from Staten Island
由史坦登島來的
we have with us Victor Strachi.
維多史特基
And the other associates that came as far as from California and Kansas City
及由加州堪薩斯來的同道
and all the other territories of the country. Thank you.
以及全國其他各地區所來的朋友 謝謝你們
How did things ever get so far?
事情怎麼會演變成如此？
I don't know.
我不曉得
It was so unfortunate, so unnecessary.
是那麼的不幸及那麼的沒必要
Tattaglia lost a son, and I lost a son.
塔塔基利亞失去了一個兒子 我也是
We're quits. And if Tattaglia agrees,
我們該停手了 若是塔塔基利亞同意
then I'm willing to let things go on as before.
我願意讓事情恢復以前的局面
We're grateful to Don Corleone for calling this meeting.
我們都很感謝柯里昂閣下 召開這次會議
We all know him as a man of his word. A modest man who listens to reason.
我們都瞭解他是個有信用的人 他為人謙虛，總是能講道理
Yes, Don Barzini. He's too modest.
是的，巴西尼閣下，他太謙虛了
He had all the judges and politicians in his pocket.
所有的法官與政客 沒有不聽他指示的
He refused to share them.
他卻拒絕與我們分享
When did I ever refuse an accommodation?
我何時拒絕過與大家分享？
All of you know me.
在座的全都認識我
When did I ever refuse, except one time? And why?
除了一次以外，我何時拒絕過？ 你們知道為甚麼
Because I believe this drug business will destroy us in the years to come.
因為我相信毒品生意 在往後幾年會毀了我們
It's not like gambling or liquor or even women,
這不像賭、酒和女人
which is something that most people want, but is forbidden by the Church.
這些是人們想要的東西 只是教會不准我們做而已
Even the police that have helped us in the past with gambling and other things
即使警察過去在賭博等方面 願意協助我們
are going to refuse to help us when it comes to narcotics.
但一提到毒品 他們會拒絕幫忙
I believed that then and I believe that now.
我以前那麼想 現在想法依然不變
Times have changed.
時代變了
It's not like the old days, when we could do anything we wanted.
不像昔日了 我們能做任何我們想做的事
A refusal is not the act of a friend.
你拒絕合作實在不夠朋友
If Don Corleone had all the judges and politicians, then he must share them
柯里昂閣下握有全紐約法律界以及 政客的勢力，他就必須與大家分享
or let others use them. He must let us draw the water from the well.
讓大家都能利用他們，他必須讓 我們分汲利益，大家一起發財
Certainly he can present a bill for such services.
當然他能因這種服務 而向大家收費
After all, we're not communists.
畢竟我們不是共產黨
I also don't believe in drugs.
我同樣的也不相信毒品
For years I paid my people extra, so they wouldn't do that kind of business.
多年來我付手下優厚的待遇 使他們不去沾毒品
Somebody says to them " I have powders."
避免有人來找他們 並且說我有白粉
" If you put up 3-4,000 dollar investment,
你只要投資三千元到四千元
we can make 50,000 distributing."
就可以賺到五萬元
They can't resist. I want to control it as a business, keep it respectable.
他們怎能抗拒得了 我想以正派的方法來經營毒品生意
I don't want it near schools, I don't want it sold to children.
我不要它們接近學校 我不要把它們賣給孩子
Thats an infàmia.
那是殘害幼苗
In my city we would keep the traffic to the colored.
我只想賣給那些黑人 或是在有色人種中流通
They're animals, so let them lose their souls.
他們反正是動物 所以讓他們去墮落吧
I hoped that we could come here and reason together.
我本希望能合理的討論一些事
And I'm willing to do whatever is necessary to find a peaceful solution.
身為一個講道理的人 我願意為此事找個和平解決之道
We are agreed. The traffic in drugs will be permitted, but controlled.
那麼我們全都達成協議 毒品生意可以做但要有限制
Don Corleone will give us protection in the east, and there will be peace.
柯里昂閣下會給我們東部的保護 然後我們和平相處
I must have strict assurance from Corleone.
但我必須有柯里昂閣下的確切保證
As time goes by and his position becomes stronger,
萬一他的地位越來越堅固之後
will he attempt any individual vendetta?
他是否會採取復仇行動
We are all reasonable men. We don't have to give assurances.
聽著，我們這全是講理的人 我們不需像是律師般給甚麼確切保證
You talk about vengeance.
你談到復仇
Will vengeance bring your son back to you?
復仇會讓你的兒子復活嗎？
Or my boy to me?
或者我的兒子？
I forgo the vengeance of my son.
我不會再去計較我兒子的死
But I have selfish reasons.
但我有個自私的要求
My youngest son was forced to leave this country
我的小兒子被迫離開這個國家
because of this Sollozzo business.
全都因為這索拉索的事
And I have to make arrangements to bring him back here safely.
我必須安排讓他安全的回來
Cleared of all these false charges.
洗脫種種無中生有的罪名
But I'm a superstitious man.
而我是個迷信的人
If an unlucky accident should befall him, if he should be shot by a police officer,
若是他不幸發生意外 或被警察開槍打死
or if he should hang himself in his jail cell,
或在牢裡上吊
or if he's struck by a bolt of lightning,
或是他被閃電擊中
then I'm going to blame some of the people in this room.
那我會怪罪於在這房間內的諸位
And that I do not forgive.
到那時候我就不會再客氣了
But, that aside
但除了那個以外
let me say that I swear
我以我孫子的性命發誓
on the souls of my grandchildren,
我不會是打破
that I will not be the one to break the peace we've made here today.
我們今天和議的人
Should I insist that all of Tattaglia's drug middlemen have clean records?
當我見塔塔基利亞的人時
Mention it. Don't insist.
提出來無妨，不要堅持
- Barzini will know without being told. - You mean Tattaglia.
-巴西尼這種人你不說他也明白 -你是說塔塔基利亞
Tattaglia's a pimp.
塔塔基利亞是個下三濫
He could never have outfought Santino.
他根本沒本事幹掉山提諾
But I didn't know until this day that it was Barzini all along.
我在今天以前並不曉得 一直是巴西尼在主使
Come on, Nancy.
來吧！南西
Keep together, everyone. Brian.
大家緊跟在一起，布萊恩
Okay, all right.
好的…
How long have you been back?
你回來多久了？
I've been back a year.
一年了
Longer than that, I think.
也許還不只
It's good to see you, Kay.
見到你真好，凱
I'm working for my father now, Kay.
我現在為我父親做事
He's been sick. Very sick.
他病了，病得很重
But you're not like him.
但是你不像他，麥克
You told me you weren't going to become like your father.
我以為你不會成為令尊那樣的人 那是你所告訴我的
My father is no different than any other powerful man.
家父與其他有權的人一樣
Any man who's responsible for other people.
就是那種要對其他人負責任的人
Like a senator or president.
像是參議員或是總統
- How naive you sound. - Why?
-你知道你說這些話有多天真 -為甚麼？
They don't have men killed.
參議員及總統不殺人
Who's being naive, Kay?
是誰天真？凱
My father's way of doing things is over. Even he knows that.
家父做事的那一套已過時了 連他都曉得那一點
In five years the Corleone family is going to be completely legitimate.
我是說在五年之內 柯里昂家族會完全合法化
Trust me. That's all I can tell you about my business. Kay...
相信我！我很清楚我未來的走向 凱…
Michael, why did you come here? Why?
麥克，你為何到這來？為甚麼？
What do you want with me after all this time?
你究竟想要我怎麼樣？這麼多年來 你不打電話也不寫信
I came because I need you. I care for you.
我來這是因為我需要你，我關心你
- Please stop it, Michael. - Because... I want you to marry me.
-別再說了，麥克 -因為…我要你嫁給我
- It's too late. - Please, Kay...
-太遲了… -凱…
I'll do anything you ask to make up for what's happened to us.
我會做任何事 以彌補過去所發生的事
Because that's important, Kay. Because what's important is that
因為那很重要！凱 重要的是因為…
we have each other. That we have a life together.
我們擁有彼此 而且我們要共度一生
That we have children. Our children.
我們會有孩子，我們的孩子
Kay, I need you.
凱，我需要你
And I love you.
而且我愛你
Barzini's people chisel my territory and we do nothing about it!
巴西尼的人搶我們的地盤 而我們卻無能為力
- Soon I'll have no place to hang my hat! - Be patient.
再過不久布魯克林 我連落腳的地方都沒有了
I'm not asking for help. Just take off the handcuffs.
我不是求你幫忙，只是不想受制肘
- Be patient. - We must protect ourselves.
-再忍耐點 -我們必須保護自己
- Let me recruit some new men. - No.
-給我個機會再培養一些新人 -不！
- Barzini would get an excuse to fight. - Mike, you're wrong.
-我不要給巴西尼藉口來開戰 -麥克，你錯了
Don Corleone...
柯里昂閣下
You once said that one day Tessio and me could form our own family.
你曾說過要讓我與泰西歐自立門戶
Till today I would never think of it. I must ask your permission.
今天以前我想都不敢想 但現在我要求你的批准
Michael is now head of the family.
現在由麥克當家
If he gives his permission, then you have my blessing.
如果他答應我就祝福你
After we make the move to Nevada
等我們搬到內華達州後
you can leave the Corleone family and go on your own.
你就可由柯里昂家族分出 自立門戶
- How long will that be? - Six months.
-那得花多少時間？ -六個月
Forgive me, but with you gone,
原諒我，教父，但當你走了後
me and Pete will come under Barzini's thumb.
我與彼得遲早會成為巴西尼的靶
I hate that Barzini. In six months' time there will be nothing left to build on.
我恨那該死的巴西尼，六個月之後 我們已經搞不出甚麼玩意了
- Do you have faith in my judgment? - Yes.
-你對我的判斷有信心嗎？ -是的
- Do I have your loyalty? - Always, Godfather.
-你仍對我忠心嗎？ -是的，忠心不二，教父
Then be a friend to Michael. Do as he says.
那麼就當麥克的朋友吧 照他所說的去做
Things are negotiated that'll solve your problems and answer your questions.
現在有些事仍在磋商 你們的問題和困難全都可以得到解決
That's all I can tell you now.
目前我只能這麼說
Carlo, you grew up in Nevada.
卡洛，你在內華達長大的
When we make our move there, you'll be my right-hand man.
當我們搬的時候 你會是我的左右手
Tom Hagen is no longer consigliere. He'll be our lawyer in Vegas.
湯姆哈金不再做軍師了 他將會擔任我們在拉斯維加斯的律師
That's no reflection on Tom, just how I want it.
我對湯姆沒有不滿 但我不要他再當軍師
If I ever need help, who's a better consigliere than my father? That's it.
況且有我父親在 他可以做我最佳的軍師，就是這樣了
- Thank you, Papa. - I'm happy for you, Carlo.
-謝謝，爸爸 -我為你高興，卡洛
Mike... Why am I out?
麥克，我為何出局了？
You're not a wartime consigliere, Tom.
你不適合當亂局中的軍師
Things may get rough with the move.
我們一搬到內華達後 事情會變得更棘手
Tom.
湯姆
I advised Michael. I never thought you were a bad consigliere.
我向麥克建議過 我從未認為你不適合當軍師
I thought Santino was a bad Don, rest in peace.
我認為山提諾不適合當家 願他安息
Michael has all my confidence, just as you do.
我信任麥克和你一樣
But there are reasons why you must have no part in what is going to happen.
但是…不讓你參與往後的行動 是有理由的
- Maybe I could help. - You're out, Tom.
-我多少能幫得上忙 -用不著了，湯姆
I can't get over the way your face looks. So good!
我實在無法不去注意你的臉 它的確看起來很棒
This doctor did some job. Did Kay talk you into it? Hey, hey, hey!
這位醫生的工夫確實不錯 是凱說服你去的嗎？慢著！
Leave them out here. He's tired and wants to clean up.
把它們留下這，我們待會再處理它們 他累了，他想梳洗一下
Let me open the door, all right?
好了，讓我來開門，好嗎？
- Hello, Mike! Welcome to Las Vegas! - All for you, kid! It's all his idea.
-麥克！歡迎光臨拉斯維加斯！ -你認為如何？全是他的主意，對吧？
- Your brother Freddy. - Girls?
-你的哥哥弗雷多 -是你弄來的女孩子，不是嗎？
I'll be right back. Keep them occupied.
我馬上回來，你先招呼一下
- Anything you want, kid, anything. - Who are the girls?
-你要甚麼全都有 -那些女孩子是誰？
- That's for you to find out. - Get rid of them, Fredo.
-這得要你自己去弄清楚了 -把她們弄走，弗雷多
- Hey, Mike... - I'm here on business. Get rid of them.
麥克
I'm tired. Get rid of the band too.
我累了，把樂隊也弄走
Hey, take off. Take off. Let's go.
走吧！走就對了
Hey, that's it. Hey, Angelo.
快點！安琪拉，快走
Hey, come on! Scram!
走吧！閃了！
Come on, honey. I don't know what's the matter with him, Johnny.
走吧，親愛的，走了，我不知道 強尼，我不知道他是怎麼回事
Sorry.
對不起
I don't know. He's tired.
我不知道，他大概累了
What happened to Moe Greene?
莫格林呢？
He had some business. He said to give him a call when the party started.
他說他有別的事 他說派對開始時，給他個電話
Well, give him a call.
那就打電話給他
- Johnny, how are you? - Nice to see you, Mike.
-強尼，你好嗎？ -麥克，再看到你真高興
- We're proud of you. - Thanks.
-我們全都以你為傲 -謝謝，麥克
Sit down, I want to talk to you. The Don is proud too.
坐，強尼，我要跟你談談 教父也以你為傲，強尼
Well, I owe it all to him.
我的一切都歸功於他
He knows how grateful you are.
他知道你會感恩
That's why he'd like to ask a favor of you.
所以他想請你幫個忙
Mike, what can I do?
麥克，我能做些甚麼？
We're thinking of giving up our interests
柯里昂家族想放棄
in the olive oil business and settling here.
橄欖油的生意 而在這裡安頓下來
Moe will sell us his share of the casino and the hotel, so we'll own all of it.
莫格林會把他旅館及賭場的股份 賣給我們使得家族能擁有全部的生意
- Tom! - Are you sure?
-湯姆！ -麥克，這點你確定嗎？
Moe loves the business. He never said nothing about selling.
莫格林很愛這門生意 從未對我提過要賣掉它的事
I'll make him an offer he can't refuse.
我會提個他無法拒絕的條件
See, Johnny...
知道嗎？強尼…
We figure that entertainment would draw gamblers to the casino.
我們認為表演一定可以 吸引賭客到賭場來
We hope you'll sign a contract to appear five times a year.
我們希望你簽個合約 一年來此登台五次
Perhaps convince some of your friends in the movies to do the same.
也許…順便找些你電影圈中的朋友
We're counting on you.
我指望你了
Sure, Mike. I'll do anything for my godfather.
當然，麥克，為了教父 我甚麼都肯做，你曉得的
Good.
很好
Hey, Mike! Hello, fellows. Everybody's here. Freddy, Tom.
麥克，各位好，大家都在這 弗雷多，湯姆…
- Good to see you. - How are you, Moe?
-見到你真好，麥克 -你好嗎？莫
Have everything? Specially prepared food, the best dancers, and good credit.
你點的都到齊了嗎？大廚會為你 煮最好吃的菜，還有最棒的舞群
Draw chips for everybody, so they can play on the house.
給房間裡的每個人都弄點籌碼來 好讓他們到場子裡去玩玩
Is my credit good enough to buy you out?
我的信用好的夠買下你的股份嗎？
Buy me out?
買我的股份？
The casino, the hotel.
賭場，這家旅館
The Corleone family wants to buy you out.
柯里昂家族想買下你全部的生意
The Corleone family wants to buy me out? No, I buy you out.
柯里昂家族想買下我全部的生意？ 不，我買下你們的，你不能買下我的
Your casino loses money. We can do better.
你的賭場在賠錢 也許我們能經營得好一點
- You think I'm skimming off the top? - You're unlucky.
-你認為我在走下坡了？麥克 -你運氣不好
You Guineas make me laugh.
你他媽的別讓我笑了
I took Freddy in when you had a bad time, and now you try to push me out!
在你們有難時，我幫你們的忙 給弗雷多一份差事
You did that because we bankrolled your casino
慢著，你讓弗雷多來這 是因為柯里昂家族支援你的賭場
and the Molinari family guaranteed his safety.
因為海岸的莫倫納家族保證他的安全 現在我們在談生意，別岔開話題
Yes. First of all, you're all done.
好，我們來談生意，麥克 首先，你們都完蛋了
You don't have that kind of muscle anymore.
柯里昂家族已經衰退了
The Godfather is sick. You're getting chased out of New York by the others.
教父生病了，對吧？ 你們被巴西尼及其他家族趕出了紐約
Do you think you can come to my hotel and take over?
你以為這裡是甚麼？ 你以為能到我的地盤上來接管？
I talked to Barzini. I can make a deal with him and still keep my hotel!
我和巴西尼談過了，我有辦法 和他打交道，也不至於失去旅館
Is that why you slapped my brother around in public?
所以你當眾支使我哥哥？
That was nothing, Mike. Moe didn't mean nothing by that.
不，麥克，那不算甚麼 莫也不是那個意思
He flies off the handle sometimes, but we're good friends.
當然他偶爾說話很大聲但是… 莫和我是好朋友，對吧？莫
I have a business to run. I've got to kick asses sometimes.
我是在做事業！ 當然要催緊點，事情才會順利
We had an argument, so I had to straighten him out.
我是偶爾和弗雷多意見不合 只不過是為了「訓練」他一下
You straightened my brother out?
你「訓練」我哥哥？
He was banging cocktail waitresses! Players couldn't get a drink.
他跟酒廊的女侍鬼混 客人喝酒沒人送
What's wrong with you?
你是怎麼回事？
I leave for New York tomorrow. Think about a price.
我明天回紐約 你考慮一個價錢吧
I'm Moe Greene! I made my bones when you were out with cheerleaders.
你知道我是誰嗎？我是莫格林 我發跡時你還在玩泥巴
Wait a minute, Moe. I have an idea.
等一等，莫，我有個主意
Tom, you're the consigliere. Talk to the Don...
湯姆！湯姆，你是軍師 你可以和教父談，解釋給他聽
Just a minute. Don is semi-retired and Mike is in charge of the family business.
慢著！教父已經半退休了 家族現在由麥克管事
If you have anything to say, say it to Michael.
你有話就向麥克說吧
Mike, you don't come to Las Vegas and talk to a man like Moe Greene like that!
麥克，你不能到拉斯維加斯來 和莫格林那種人那樣說話
Fredo...
弗雷多
You're my older brother, and I love you.
你是我哥，我愛你
But don't ever take sides with anyone against the family again.
但不准你再聯合外人 起來反對自己家族
Ever.
絕對不准
I have to see my father and his people, so have dinner without me.
我必須先去看我父親和他的手下 你們先吃飯吧
This weekend we'll go out. We'll go to the city, see a show and have dinner.
這個週末我們可以出外遊玩 到城裡看電影吃飯，我保證
Your sister wants to ask you something.
麥克，麥克，你姐姐有事想問你
- Let her ask. - She's afraid to.
-她可以問我！ -她怕你
They want you to be godfather to their boy.
康妮和卡洛要你當他們孩子的教父
- We'll see. - Will you?
-到時再說吧！ -你會嗎？
Let me think about it. Come on.
讓我考慮一下 到時再說，來吧
Barzini will move against you first.
巴西尼想要先對付你
He'll set up a meeting with someone you absolutely trust.
他會找個你信任的人來安排見面
Guaranteeing your safety.
並保證你的安全
And at that meeting you'll be assassinated.
但你一出席會議，他就殺了你
I like to drink wine more than I used to.
我現在比以前愛喝酒了
- Anyway, I'm drinking more. - It's good for you, Pop.
-而且越愛喝就喝的越多 -對你有好處的，爸爸
I don't know.
我不知道
Are you happy with your wife and children?
你太太和小孩過的還快樂吧？
- Very happy. - That's good.
-非常快樂 -很好
I hope you don't mind the way I keep going over this Barzini business.
希望你不介意我一直在談巴西尼
- No, not at all. - It's an old habit.
-不，一點也不 -這是我的老習慣
I spend my life trying not to be careless.
我花了一輩子就學會了「小心」
Women and children can be careless, but not men.
女人和小孩能夠粗心大意 但男人不行
- How's your boy? - He's good.
-你兒子還好嗎？ -很好
He looks more like you every day.
你知道他越來越像你了
He's smarter than I am. He's three and can read the funny papers.
他比我聰明 才三歲就懂得看漫畫了
Read the funny papers.
看漫畫
I want you to arrange for a telephone man to check all in-and out-going calls.
我要你安排一個電話公司的人 查每一個進出這裡的電話
I did it already. I took care of that, Pop.
-我已經做了，爸 -任何一個人都有可能
That's right. I forgot.
-爸！我已經處理那件事了 -沒錯，我忘了
What's the matter?
怎麼回事？
What's bothering you?
是甚麼困擾著你？
I'll handle it. I told you I can handle it, so I'll handle it.
我應付得了，我說能，我就能
I knew that Santino would have to go through all this.
我知道山提諾勢必會染指家族事業
And Fredo...
還有弗雷多
Fredo was, well...
弗雷多他…
But I never wanted this for you.
但我從來沒… 我從來沒想到要你參與
I worked my whole life. I don't apologize for taking care of my family.
我幹了一輩子，沒甚麼遺憾的 我照顧了我的家人
And I refused to be a fool,
但是我絕不當傻瓜
dancing on a string held by all those big shots.
讓那些大人物在幕後操縱我
I don't apologize. That's my life, but I thought that,
我不必道歉，那是我的命運 但是我想過…
that when it was your time, you would be the one to hold the strings.
有一天你能當那些操縱的人
Senator Corleone. Governor Corleone. Something.
柯里昂參議員 柯里昂州長之類的
Another pezzonovante.
再建立一個王國
Well...
這個…
Just wasn't enough time, Michael. Wasn't enough time.
時間不多了，麥克，時間不多了
We'll get there, Pop. We'll get there.
我們會做到的，爸，我們會做到的
Now listen, whoever comes to you with this Barzini meeting,
你聽好…誰請你去和巴西尼開會
he's the traitor. Don't forget that.
他就是叛徒，千萬別忘了
Can I hold it, please?
能讓我拿嗎？我能自己澆水
- Can I water these? - Yes, go ahead.
-我可以澆水嗎？ -可以，澆吧！
Over here, over here.
這裡，來這裡
Be careful. You're spilling it.
小心點，別濺到了，小心
Anthony!
安東尼，過來，來吧…
Come here, come here.
來這裡
That's it. We'll put it right there.
對了，放在這
I'll show you something. Come here.
來，有東西給你看，來這
Stand there.
你站好
Give me an orange!
把柳丁給我
That's a new trick.
別怕，這是新把戲
You run in there. Run in there.
你去裡面，去裡面
Where are you?
你在哪？
Mike, can I have a minute?
麥克，能借一步說話嗎？
Barzini wants to arrange a meeting.
巴西尼想要安排一次會議
He says we can straighten out any of our problems.
他說任何的問題 都可以談出一個解決之道
- You talked to him? - Yeah.
-你和他談過了？ -是的
I can arrange security. On my territory.
我能安排安全事宜
Do you know how they're going to come at you?
你知道他們預備怎麼對付你嗎？
They're arranging a meeting in Brooklyn. Tessio's ground.
他們安排在布魯克林開會 泰西歐的地盤上
Where I'll be safe.
說在那我會安全的
I always thought it would be Clemenza, not Tessio.
我一直以為是克裏曼沙 沒想到是泰西歐
It's the smart move. Tessio was always smarter.
這一招漂亮，泰西歐一向聰明
But I'm going to wait.
但我會靜觀其變
After the baptism.
等洗禮過了再說
I've decided to be godfather to Connie's baby.
我決定當康妮小孩的教父了
And then I'll meet with Don Barzini and Tattaglia.
然後我再去見巴西尼 還有塔塔基利亞
All the heads of the five families. 1230.1
所有五大家族的族長
Go forth from him, unclean spirit, 1230.2
（義大利文禱詞）
Michael, do you believe in God, the Father, Creator of Heaven and Earth?
麥克，你相信上帝嗎？ 全能的天父，萬物的創造者
I do.
我相信
Do you believe in Jesus Christ, His only Son, our Lord?
你相信耶穌基督 他的獨子，我們的主嗎？
I do.
我相信
Do you believe in the Holy Ghost, the Holy Catholic Church?
你相信聖靈，神聖的教堂嗎？
Our Father, who art in heaven, hallowed be thy name. 1236.2
（義大利文禱詞）
Michael Francis Rizzi, do you renounce Satan?
麥克柯里昂，你棄絕撒旦嗎？
I do renounce him.
我棄絕
And all his works?
包括他所有的作為嗎？
- And all his pomps? - I do renounce them.
-包括他所有的虛偽？ -我棄絕
Michael Rizzi, will you be baptized?
麥克柯里昂 你願意當他的教父嗎？
I will. 1244.1
我願意
In the name of the Father, 1244.2
（義大利文禱詞）
Michael Rizzi, go in peace, and may the Lord be with you. Amen.
麥克柯里昂 願主與你同在，阿們
Kay!
凱
Kiss your godfather.
這是你的教父！
- Carlo. - What? Can't go to Vegas. Something's come up.
卡洛，我現在不能去拉斯維加斯 臨時有要事
Everybody has to leave without us.
讓他們先走吧！
- Mike, it's our first vacation! - Connie, please.
-麥克，這是我們第一次度假 -康妮，別吵
Go back to the house, wait for my call. It's important.
-你要我怎麼做？ -回家去等我電話，有要事
I'll only be a couple of days.
我只需一兩天
We're on our way to Brooklyn.
我們要去布魯克林了
- I hope Mike can get us a good deal. - I'm sure he will.
-我希望麥克今晚能談個好交易 -他一定會的
Sal, Tom, the boss says he'll come in a separate car, so you two go on ahead.
沙爾、湯姆，老闆說他自己坐車來 叫你們先走
- That screws up my arrangements. - That's what he said.
-他不能那麼做，弄亂了我所有的安排 -他是這麼說的
I can't go either, Sal.
我也不能去，沙爾
Tell Mike it was only business. I always liked him.
告訴麥克這純粹是生意 我一直都喜歡他
- He understands that. - Excuse me, Sal.
-他會瞭解的，沙爾 -抱歉了，沙爾
Tom, can you get me off the hook?
湯姆，能替我求個情嗎？
- For old times' sake? - Can't do it, Sally.
-看在老交情的份上 -我做不到，沙爾
You have to answer for Santino, Carlo.
你得為山尼的事償命，卡洛
- Mike, you got it all wrong. - You fingered Sonny for Barzini.
-你誤會了，麥克 -你為巴西尼的人設計害山尼
That little farce you played with my sister.
你和我姐姐演的那場鬧劇
- You think that could fool a Corleone? - I'm innocent. I swear on the kids.
以為騙得過柯里昂家的人嗎？
- Please, don't do this. - Sit down.
-求你，麥克，別這樣對我 -坐下
Don't do this to me, please.
麥克，別這樣對我，求你
Barzini is dead.
巴西尼死了！
So is Philip Tattaglia.
菲立浦塔塔基利亞也死了
Moe Greene.
還有莫格林
Strachi. Cuneo.
史特基、克裏安諾
Today I settle all family business, so don't tell me you're innocent, Carlo.
今天我一次清理整個家族的事 所以別跟我說你是無辜的，卡洛
Admit what you did.
承認你所做過的
Get him a drink.
給他一杯酒
Come on.
說吧！
Don't be afraid, Carlo.
別怕，卡洛
Do you think I'd make my sister a widow?
你以為我忍心讓我姐姐當寡婦？
I'm godfather to your son, Carlo.
我又是你兒子的教父，卡洛
Go ahead, drink, drink.
喝吧！
No, you're out of the family business. That's your punishment.
卡洛，從此你退出家族的生意 這是給你的懲罰
You're finished. I'm putting you on a plane to Vegas.
你玩完了 我送你上飛機去拉斯維加斯
Tom.
湯姆
I want you to stay there. Understand?
我要你留在那邊，明白嗎？
Only don't tell me you're innocent.
只是別告訴我你是無辜的
Because it insults my intelligence. Makes me very angry.
因為那等於把我當傻瓜 會讓我非常生氣
Who approached you?
現在，是誰和你接頭的？
Tattaglia or Barzini?
塔塔基利亞還是巴西尼？
It was Barzini.
是巴西尼
Good.
好
There's a car waiting outside to take you to the airport.
外面有輛車等著送你去機場
I'll call your wife and tell her what flight you're on.
我通知你太太說你坐那班飛機
- Mike... - Get out of my sight.
-麥克，我… -快走，別讓我看到你
Hello, Carlo.
卡洛
- I'm trying to tell you... - Mama, please!
-我想告訴你… -媽媽，拜託…
Michael!
麥克！
- What is it? - Where is he?
-怎麼了？ -他在哪兒？麥克
Michael, you lousy bastard! You killed my husband.
麥克，你這混蛋，你殺了我丈夫
You waited until Papa died, so nobody could stop you.
你看爸一死，就沒人能管你了 所以你就把他殺了
You blamed him for Sonny. Everybody did.
你一直把山尼的死怪在他身上 你一直如此，大家都如此
But you never thought about me! Now what are we going to do?
但你有沒有想過我？從來不在乎我 我以後要怎麼辦？
Connie.
康妮…
Why do you think he kept Carlo at the Mall?
你以為他為何要卡洛在他身邊
He knew he was going to kill him.
他早就算計好要殺他
And you stood godfather to our baby. You lousy cold-hearted bastard!
你還是我孩子的教父 你這個冷酷的混蛋
Want to know how many men he had killed with Carlo? Read the papers!
你知道除了卡洛 他還殺過多少人嗎？
That's your husband, that's your husband!
是你丈夫…
No! No, no...
不要！…
Take her upstairs. Get her a doctor.
帶她上樓，找醫生來
She's hysterical.
她神經錯亂了
Hysterical.
歇斯底里
Michael, is it true?
麥克，是真的嗎？
- Don't ask me about my business, Kay. - Is it true?
-我跟你說過別管公事，凱 -是真的嗎？
Don't ask me about my business. Enough!
別過問我的公事
All right.
好吧！
This one time.
只此一次
This one time I'll let you ask me about my affairs.
這次我讓你問吧！
Is it true?
是真的嗎？
No.
不是
I guess we both need a drink. Come on.
我想我們兩個都需要喝一杯 我去倒
Don Corleone.
柯里昂閣下